That fat is called docosahexaenoic acid
or DHA as you might know it. Or you
might know it as a particular omega-3
fat. And in an extensive analysis of 48
studies, researchers seem to think that
it reduces our risk of developing
dementia, a series of brain-related
disorders. But is that what the science
here in actually shows? And is the
evidence really strong enough to make
that case? And if so, how much DHA is
necessary to experience that benefit?
So, the researchers pulled 48 studies
into what's called a systematic review.
It's a review of the studies that
follows a certain rules and guidelines
for exactness and reliability. But
beyond that, they also included a large
chunk of these studies into a
meta-analysis, which means that all the
data is combined to tease out any
potential relationships like reduced
risk of dementia, which they then
transformed into a quantified network
collation, which I just made up. It
doesn't exist, but it seems to fit the
nerdiness of what I just described. So,
here we are. Anyway, when we pull all
these data together, we discover that
DHA is linked to reduce dementia risk.
But importantly, it wasn't just dietary
intake of DHA that was looked at, but
also the amount found in the blood and
the amount specifically integrated into
your cells.
Now,
that's a key distinction because
consuming omega-3s at the time of the
researchers measure DHA intake does not
guarantee omega-3s, remember that's the
fat class that DHA belongs to, have been
consumed for long periods of time, which
is necessary for omega-3s like DHA to be
integrated, actually added into the
structure of our cells. I'll discuss how
to apply all that to our lives later on,
but for now, just know that looking at
membrane DHA is better long-term marker
of DHA consumption. So, I've simplified
the data here. We have three different
ways of assessing DHA on the left side.
So, the yellow line going up indicates
neutral or no link between DHA and
dementia risk. Now, if the red line
moves to the left without touching the
yellow line, there's a link with reduced
dementia risk. As you can see, dietary
and likely erythrocyte membrane
integrated DHA track with reduced risk,
but plasma DHA does not. Now, there's a
simple explanation for that, like the
fact that plasma DHA may be measured
from a smaller number of studies, making
it more difficult to detect an effect.
Or plasma DHA may simply be a bad way to
detect an effect relative to the other
two. Or plenty of other explanations.
So, the takeaway here is that the
omega-3 fat docosahexaenoic acid, so
DHA, is associated with reduced dementia
risk. Now,
there are two problems that I want to
bring to your attention here because
they matter in this moving forward to
discuss dosing in some other context.
First, since all the studies included in
this analysis were associative studies,
the researchers have to do a series of
adjustments to control for other factors
that may influence the results that we
just saw, the protection against
dementia.
So, if you've been following Physionic
for a while, you already know that. But
one major drawback of doing
meta-analyses in associative studies is
that all these studies use different
adjustments, so meaning that like one
study may adjust for body weight,
genetic factors, blood pressure, and
another might adjust for genetic factors
and blood pressure, but instead of body
weight, they adjust for blood sugar
levels. Now, think about the uncertainty
that introduces in the relationships
that we're seeing here when that's the
case across all these studies. So, here
are the common adjustments used. Two,
the length of the studies varied with a
few lasting less than a year, which
makes it unsurprising that some of these
studies would show no effect if
dementia, a series of diseases that take
time to develop, doesn't have the time
to develop. This is a minor issue as
most of the studies lasted many years,
even decades. Now, I'm pointing these
things out simply, and there's plenty
more that I could point out because I
want you to understand that analyzing
studies isn't just reading the title and
the abstract. There's a lot of critical
thinking, some compromise and
limitations that go into an analysis of
a study. So, when someone hops on social
media and someone's pointing at a study
title or even explaining the basic
conclusions of the study, there's
probably a thousand rivulets of context
that they've just bulldozed over to
reach the headline as quickly as
possible. Still, does that mean that the
title of this video is nonsense?
No. And not because I want it to be
true, but because the researchers did
something else quite clever that
addresses some of our concerns here.
They actually did a separate analysis on
about a thousand individuals for up to
six years to identify exactly how many
people developed Alzheimer's, so that's
a specific type of dementia. Now, I'll
still admit that a thousand people to
detect a specific disease state is quite
a small study in the way that it's
designed. But it does solve some of the
earlier issues.
One, now we have raw data that we can
apply our own adjustments to, and
therefore we know exactly what we're
controlling for. And two, the length of
the studies defined and probably long
enough to detect a relationship. And if
I simplify the data for you here, we're
looking at Alzheimer's disease risk in
these 1,000 individuals over the six
years or up to six years.
The same rules apply. So, the beneficial
relationship is in the red lines moved
to the left of the yellow line.
Notice that general exposure to omega-3
fats reduced Alzheimer's disease risk.
But when we split the data by the length
of consumption, there's a much more
certain and potent relationship with
long-term exposure. Now, if we marry
these data with the previous showing
improvements in total dementia, why not
omega-3s, so DHA in that case,
are actually integrated into our cells.
This actually makes a lot of sense.
Essentially, the lesson here is that
omega-3 consumption needs to be
consistent. Allow me to quick note that
they did not find this relationship with
DHA alone. And that's actually
unsurprising considering that the size
of the study, and they could only assess
blood markers for DHA in 800
participants, so an even smaller group.
Again, compromises and limitations. The
main point here is that omega-3s as a
whole track with reduced Alzheimer's
risk, but only when consumed regularly
over the long term.
So, the next question is, of course,
what is the long term? What does that
mean? And how much is going to actually
offer these benefits to you and me?
Let's get into that next. But if you're
interested in understanding the
relationship omega-3s have based on
genetic risk, so people carrying an
Alzheimer's linked gene APOE4, or if age
plays a role, or even other types of
omega-3s like EPA and ALA, and if they
carry benefit against dementia, and my
recommendations on tested sources of
omega-3s, then be sure to check out the
extended version of this video that
you're watching. It's part of my
Physionic Insider membership. If you're
a reader, all the videos also come with
articles. And if you want it delivered
to your email every week along with a
one-paragraph summary of the most
important points, all of that is
included with an Insider membership.
Plus, what's this?
More? Yeah, a lot more perks of being an
Insider. Check it out. The link is to
join it is in the description box, and
you get access to everything.
Okay, we're talking about 10 years or
longer. So, people who consume DHA for a
decade or longer have a 64% reduced
Alzheimer's disease risk based on this
analysis.
As for the amount, check this out. We're
looking at DHA consumed on the
horizontal axis. The vertical axis is
dementia risk. If the lines go down,
that's an indication of reduced dementia
risk. So, I don't need to spell it out
more than that. You can see, it's pretty
clear, linear reduction in risk with
more DHA consumption all the way down to
1 g of DHA.
The point here is
consuming up to 1 g of DHA per day for
10 plus years relates to reduced
dementia risk. Now, does that
necessarily mean supplementation?
It does not. While some studies
specifically looked at supplementation,
many group supplementation with
consuming food sources of omega-3s like
fatty fish. So, where does that leave
us? What's the take-home messages here?
I will add here that there are
weaknesses to this study, some that we
went over, some that we haven't, which
are inherent to this type of analysis.
However, pairing the strengths of this
study plus my past analyses looking at
intervention studies, so meaning uh
studies that feed omega-3s to people and
then measure their cognitive
performance, I think that we have strong
evidence that omega-3s, especially DHA,
improve cognitive function, protect
against dementia, and should be consumed
up to 1 g per day, possibly more, we
don't know, over the long term, meaning
10 years or more. Now, if you're
anything like me, you'd also be
interested in exactly what happens to
your brain when these omega-3s interact
with your brain cells. You can find that
right here. It's a fascinating world
trying to understand how these fats
become part of your brain structure.
I'll speak with you over there.
I hope this helped, and I'll catch you
in the next one. Bye.